Wonder by R. J. Palacio.
Part 8. August.
You're going to reach the sky. Fly, beautiful child. your Rhythmix, beautiful child.
the fifth grade nature retreat.
EVERY YEAR IN the spring,, the fifth graders of Beecher Prep go away for 3
days and 2 nights to a place called Broarwood Nature Reserve in
Pennsylvania.. It’s a 4-hour bus drive away..
The kids sleep in cabins with bunk beds..
There are campfires and s’mores and long walks through the woods..
The teachers have been prepping us about this all year long,. so, all the kids in
the grade are excited about it—.
—except for me..
And it’s not even that I’m not excited,,
because I kind of am—. —it’s just I’ve never slept away from home before. and
I’m kind of nervous..
Most kids have had sleepovers by the time they’re my age.. A lot of kids have
gone to sleepaway camps, or stayed with their grandparents or whatever..
Not me..
Not unless you include hospital stays,.
but even then, Mom or Dad always stayed with me overnight.. But I never slept
over at Tata and Papa's house, or Aunt Kate and Uncle Po’s house..
When I was really little,, that was mainly because there were too many
medical issues,. like my trach tube needing to be cleared every hour, or
reinserting my feeding tube if it got detached.. But when I got bigger,, I just
never felt like sleeping anywhere else..
There was one time when I half slept over Christopher’s house..
We were about eight, and we were still best friends.. Our family had gone for a
visit to his house, and me and Christopher were having such a great
time playing Lego Star Wars that I didn’t want to leave when it was time to go..
We were like,, "“Please,, please,, please, can we have a sleepover?”?"
So, our parents said yes,. and Mom and Dad and Via drove home.. And me and
Christopher stayed up till midnight playing,, until Lisa,, his mom,, said:,
"“Okay,, guys,, time to go to bed.”."
Well,, that’s when I kind of panicked a bit..
Lisa tried to help me go to sleep,, but I just started crying that I wanted to go
home.. So, at 1:00 a...m.., Lisa called Mom
and Dad,, and Dad drove all the way back out to Bridgeport to pick me up..
We didn’t get home until 3:00 a...m..
So, my one and only sleepover,, up until now,, was pretty much of a disaster,,
which is why I’m a little nervous about the nature retreat..
On the other hand,, I’m really excited.
Known for.
I ASKED MOM to buy me a new rolling duffel bag, because my old one had Star
Wars stuff on it,, and there was no way I was going to take that to the fifth
grade nature retreat..
As much as I love Star Wars, I didn't want that to be what I’m known for..
Everyone’s known for something in middle school.. Like, Reed is known for really
being into marine life and the oceans and things like that.. And Amos is known
for being a really good baseball player..
And Charlotte is known for having been in a TV commercial when she was six..
And Zamina is known for being really smart..
My point is, that in middle school, you kind of get known for what you’re into,,
and you have to be careful about stuff like that..
Like, Max G and Max W will never live down their Dungeons and Dragons obsession..
So, I was actually trying to ease out of the whole Star Wars thing a bit.. I mean,,
it’ll always be special to me,, like it is with the doctor who, but in
my hearing aids., It’s just not the thing I wanted to be known for in middle school..
I’m not sure what I want to be known for,, but it’s not that..
That’s not exactly true:. I do know what I’m really known for.,
But there’s nothing I can do about that..
A Star Wars duffel bag I could do something about.
Packing.
MOM HELPED ME pack the night before the big trip.. We put all the clothes I was
taking on my bed,, and she folded everything neatly and put it inside the bag while I watched..
It was a plain blue rolling duffel,, by the way:. no logos or artwork..
"“What if I can’t sleep at night?”?" I asked.. "“Take a book with you.. Then if
you can’t sleep,, you can pull out your flashlight, and read for a bit until you
get sleepy,”." she answered..
I nodded..
"“What if I have a nightmare?”?"
"“Your teachers will be there,, sweetie,”."
she said.. "“And Jack., And your friends.”."
"“I can bring Babu." I said.. That was my favorite stuffed animal when I was
little., A small black bear with a soft black nose..
"“You don’t really sleep with him anymore,, do you?”?" said Mom..
"“No,, but I keep them in my closet in case I wake up in the middle of the
night and can’t get back to sleep,”." I said..
"“I could hide him in my bag.. No one would know.”."
"“Then let’s do that.”." Mom nodded,, getting Babu from inside my closet..
"“I wish they allowed cell phones,”." I said..
"“I know,, me too!”." she said..
"“Though I know you’re going to have a great time,, Auggie.."
"You sure you want me to pack Babu?"
"Yeah,."
"but way down where no one can see him,”."
I said..
She stuck Babu deep inside the bag and then stuffed the last of my T-shirts on
top of him..
"“So many clothes for just 2 days."
"3 days and 2 nights,”." I corrected her..
"“Yep.”." She nodded,, smiling..
"“Three days and two nights.”."
She zipped up the duffel bag and picked it up..
"“Not too heavy.." "Try it.”."
I picked up the bag..
"“Fine.”." I shrugged..
She sat on the bed..
"“Hey,, what happened to your Empire Strikes Back poster?”?"
"“Oh,, I took that down ages ago,”." I answered.. She shook her head..
"“Huh,, I didn’t notice that before.”."
"“I’m trying to,, you know,, change my image a bit,”." I explained..
"“Okay.”." She smiled,, nodding like she understood..
"“Anyway,, honey,, you have to promise me you won’t forget to put on the bug
spray,, okay?? On the legs,, especially when you’re hiking through the woods..
It’s right here in the front compartment.”." "“Uh-huh.”."
"“And put on your sunscreen,”." she said..
"“You do not want to get a sunburn.. And don’t,, I repeat,, do not forget to take
your hearing aids off if you go swimming.”."
"“Would I get electrocuted?”?"
"“No,, but you’d be in real hot water with Daddy because those things cost a
fortune!”." she laughed..
"“I put the rain poncho in the front compartment,, too..
Same thing goes if it rains, Augie, okay??
Make sure you cover the hearing aids with the hood.”."
"“Aye,, aye,, sir,”." I said,, saluting..
She smiled and pulled me over..
"“I can’t believe how much you’ve grown up this year, Augie." she said softly,,
putting her hands on the sides of my face..
"“Do I look taller?”?"
"“Definitely.”." She nodded..
"“I’m still the shortest one in my grade.”."
"“I’m not really even talking about your height,”." she said.. "“Suppose I hate it there?”."
"“You’re going to have a great time, Augie.
I nodded.. She got up and gave me a quick kiss on the forehead..
“Okay,, so I say we get to bed now.”.
“It’s only 9:00, Mom!”. “Your bus leaves at 6:00 a...m.. tomorrow..
You don’t want to be late..
Come on., Chop chop.. Your teeth are brushed?”?
I nodded and climbed into bed.. She started to lie down next to me..
“You don’t need to put me to bed tonight,, Mom,”. I said..
“I’ll read on my own till I get sleepy.”.
“Really?”?
She nodded,, impressed.. She squeezed my hand and gave it a kiss..
“Okay, then. Good night, love..
Have sweet dreams.”.
“You, too.”.
She turned on the little reading light beside the bed..
“I’ll write you letters,”, I said as she was leaving..
“Even though I’ll probably be home before you guys even get them.”. “Then we can read
them together,”, she said,.
and threw me a kiss..
When she left my room,, I took my copy of The Lion,, the Witch, and the Wardrobe
off the nightstand and started reading until I fell asleep..
though the Witch knew the Deep Magic,, there is a magic deeper still which she did not know..
Her knowledge goes way back only to the dawn of time..
But if she could have looked a little further back, into the stillness and the
darkness before Time dawned,, she would have read there a different incantation.
Daybreak.
THE NEXT DAY I woke up really early.. It was still dark inside my room and even
darker outside,, though I knew it would be morning soon..
I turned over on my side but didn’t feel at all sleepy..
That’s when I saw Daisy sitting near my bed..
I mean,, I knew it wasn’t Daisy,, but for
a second I saw a shadow that looked like her..
I didn’t think it was a dream then,, but now,, looking back,, I know it must have
been..
It didn’t make me sad to see her at all:.
it just filled me up with nice feelings inside..
She was gone after a second,, and I couldn’t see her again in the darkness..
The room slowly started lightening.. I reached for my hearing aid headband and
put it on,, and now the world was really awake.. I could hear the garbage trucks
clanking down the street and the birds in our backyard.. And down the hallway, I
heard Mom’s alarm beeping..
Daisy’s ghost made me feel super strong inside,, knowing wherever I am,, she’d be
there with me..
I got up out of bed and went to my desk
and wrote a little note to Mom.. Then I went into the living room, where my
packed bag was by the door.. I opened it up and fished inside until I found what
I was looking for..
I took Baboo back to my room,, and I laid
him in my bed and taped the little note to Mom on his chest.. And then I covered
him with my blanket so Mom would find him later.. The note read:, "Dear Mom,, I
won’t need Baboo,, but if you miss me,, you can cuddle with him yourself.
XOXO, Auggie."
Day one. THE BUS RIDE went really fast..
I sat by the window and Jack was next to me in the aisle seat.. Summer and Maya
were in front of us..
Everyone was in a good mood., Kind of loud,, laughing a lot.. I noticed right
away that Julian wasn’t on our bus,, even though Henry and Miles were..
I figured he must be on the other bus,, but then I overheard Miles tell Amos
that Julian ditched the grade trip because he thought the whole nature
retreat thing was,,  , dorky..
I got totally pumped because dealing with Julian for 3 days in a row— —and two
nights— —was a major reason that I was nervous about this whole trip.. So, now
without him there,, I could really just relax and not worry about anything..
We got to the nature reserve at around noon.. The first thing we did was put our
stuff down in the cabins.. There were three bunk beds to every room,, so me and
Jack did rock,, paper,, scissors for the top bunk, and I won. Woohoo! And the
other guys in the room were Reed and Tristan, and Pablo and Nino..
After we had lunch in the main cabin,, we all went on a two-hour guided nature
hike through the woods.. But these were not woods like the kind they have in
Central Park:. these were real woods..
Giant trees that almost totally blocked out the sunlight.. Tangles of leaves and
fallen tree trunks.. Howls and chirps and really loud bird calls.. There was a
slight fog,, too,, like a pale blue smoke all around us.. So cool..
The nature guide pointed everything out to us:. the different types of trees we
were passing,. the insects inside the dead logs on the trail,. the signs of
deer and bears in the woods,. what types of birds were whistling and where to
look for them.. I realized that my low-bot hearing aids actually made me
hear better than most people, because I was usually the first person to hear a new bird call..
It started to rain as we headed back to camp.. I pulled on my rain poncho and
pulled the hood up so my hearing aids wouldn’t get wet,. but my jeans and shoes
got soaked by the time we reached our cabins.. Everyone got soaked.. It was fun,,
though.. We had a wet sock fight in the cabin..
Since it rained for the rest of the day,, we spent most of the afternoon goofing
off in the rec room.. They had a ping pong table and old-style arcade games
like Pac-Man and Missile Command that we played until dinner time. Luckily,, by
then, it had stopped raining,, so we got to have a real campfire cookout.. The log
benches around the campfire were still a little damp,, but we threw our jackets
over them and hung out by the fire,, toasting s’mores and eating the best
roasted hot dogs I have ever, ever tasted..
Mom was right about the mosquitoes:.
there were tons of them.. But luckily, I had spritzed myself before I left the
cabin,, and I wasn’t eaten alive like some of the other kids were..
I loved hanging out by the campfire after dark.. I loved the way bits of fire
dust would float up and disappear into the night air..
And how the fire lit up people’s faces..
I loved the sound the fire made,, too..
And how the woods were so dark that you couldn’t see anything around you,. and
you’d look up and see a billion stars in
the sky.. The sky doesn’t look like that in North River Heights..
I’ve seen it look like that in Montauk,, though:.
like someone sprinkled salt on a shiny black table..
I was so tired when I got back to the
cabin, and I didn’t need to pull out the book to read.. I fell asleep almost as
fast as my head hit the pillow..
And maybe I dreamed about the stars,.
I don’t know.
The fairgrounds.
THE NEXT DAY was just as great as the first day.. We went horseback riding in
the morning,, and in the afternoon, we repelled up some ginormous trees with
the help of the nature guides..
By the time we got back to the cabins for dinner,, we were all really tired again..
After dinner, they told us we had an hour to rest,, and then we were going to
take a 15-minute bus ride to the fairgrounds for an outdoor movie night..
I hadn’t had the chance to write a
letter to Mom and Dad and Via yet,. so, I wrote one telling them all about the
stuff we did that day and the day before..
I pictured myself reading it to them out loud when I got back,, since there was
just no way the letter would get home before I did..
When we got to the fairgrounds,, the sun was just starting to set.. It was about
7:30. The shadows were really long on the grass, and the clouds were pink and
orange.. It looked like someone had taken sidewalk chalk and smudged
the colors across the sky with their fingers.. It’s not that I haven’t seen
nice sunsets before in the city, because I have—. —slivers of sunsets between
buildings—. —but I wasn’t used to seeing so much sky in every direction.. Out here
in the fairgrounds,, I could understand why ancient people used to think the
world was flat and the sky was a dome
that closed in on top of it.. That’s what it looked like from the fairgrounds, in
the middle of this huge open field..
Because we were the first school to arrive,, we got to run around the field
all we wanted until the teachers told us it was time to lay out our sleeping bags
on the ground and get good viewing seats..
We unzipped our bags and laid them down like picnic blankets on the grass in
front of the giant movie screen in the middle of the field..
Then we went to the row of food trucks parked at the edge of the field to load
up on snacks and sodas and stuff like that..
There were concession stands there,, too,, like at a farmers’ market,, selling
roasted peanuts and cotton candy..
And up a little farther was a short row of carnival-type stalls,, the kind where
you can win a stuffed animal if you throw a baseball into a basket..
Jack and I both tried— —and failed— —to win anything,. but we heard Amos won a yellow
hippo and gave it to Zamina.
That was the big gossip that went around:. the jock and the brainiac..
From the food trucks,, you could see the cornstalks in back of the movie screen..
They covered about a third of the entire field.. The rest of the field was
completely surrounded by woods.. As the sun sank lower in the sky,, the tall
trees at the entrance to the woods looked dark blue..
By the time the other school buses pulled into the parking lots,, we were
back in our spots on the sleeping bags,, right smack in front of the screen:. the
best seats in the whole field..
Everyone was passing around snacks and having a great time..
Me and Jack and Summer and Reed and Maya played Pictionary..
We could hear the sound of the other schools arriving,, the loud laughing and
talking of kids coming out on the field on both sides of us,, but we couldn’t
really see them..
Though the sky was still light,, the sun had gone down completely, and everything
on the ground had turned deep purple..
The clouds were shadows now.. We had trouble even seeing the Pictionary cards in front of us..
Just then,, without any announcement,, all the lights at the ends of the field went on at once..
They were like big bright stadium lights.. I thought of that scene in Close
Encounters when the alien ship lands and they’re playing that music.
Da da doo. Don don.
Everyone in the field started applauding and cheering, like something great had just happened.
Thanks for watching. please remember to like and subscribe. Become a channel
member and we'll see you in The next video.